Guide to the Alex Harris photographs and papers, 1970-2012 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- DoubleTake Records Series, 1991-1998 and undated, (6 boxes)
  - DoubleTake recordings, 1986-1993 and undated
    [Originals closed to use. Listening copies must be made. Please consult with a reference archivist before coming to use this item.]
    - "R. Coles on Documentary Studies," 1986 Jan. 27 (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_019)
    - "R. Coles on Documentary Studies," 1986 Jan. 27 (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_020)
    - "Bob Coles/Whitney Ellsworth," 1992 May 4 (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_025)
    - "Bob Coles/Alex Harris Q.R. [i.e., Quail Roost] #1," undated [1993 May 5?] (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_026)
    - "#3 Quail Roost Retreat, Whitney Ellsworth, Alex Harris, et al.," 1993 May 5 (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_027)
    - "Bob on magazine," undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_028)
    - "DoubleTake conv. [conf.?]," undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_029)
    - "DoubleTake meeting," undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_030)
- Project Files Series, 1970-1998 and undated, (7 boxes)
  Articles, correspondence, grant applications, manuscripts, notes, photographic materials, printed materials, research notes, tape recordings, and other documents derived from various books and related exhibitions and symposia on which Harris has worked as curator, editor, organizer, or photographer. The bulk of the materials derive from the following three books and related projects: Gertrude Blom: Bearing Witness (1984); A New Life: Stories and Photographs from the Suburban South (1997); A World Unsuspected: Portraits of Southern Childhood (1987); and from South Africa: The Cordoned Heart, (1986) a project on South African photographers documenting apartheid, conducted with Omar Badsha, Bruce Payne, Margaret Sartor, and others. There are two large sets of oral history interviews on cassette tapes in this series, deriving from Harris's work with anthropologist Blom, and from his work with South African photographers.
  - Gertrude Blom Project Files, 1970-1987 and undated
    Articles, recorded interviews, correspondence, grant applications, manuscripts, research notes, card files, and other materials related to projects on anthropologist, journalist, and photographer Gertrude Duby Blom, who documented the culture and struggles of Mexican indigenous peoples such as the Lacandón. Materials center around Harris's work with Blom on the book Gertrude Blom: Bearing Witness (1984) and the related exhibition at the International Center for Photography, also 1984, co-curated by Harris and Margaret Sartor. Arranged alphabetically by topic. Photos of indigenous tribes, probably from this period, are also found in Box 57.
    The Rubenstein Library also holds a small collection of Blom's photographic prints of the Lacandón.
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Listening copies are available. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
    - Blom project files, (22 folders) (Box 51-53)
    - Mexico: small black-and-white photographs of indigenous tribes and bi-racial people (Lacandón, Ladinos, and others), circa 1983, (3 folders) (Box 57)
  - Gertrude Duby Blom Oral History Interviews, 1982 July and undated
    Eight of the cassettes are interviews conducted by Alex Harris; the ninth cassette features Blom speaking at a conference. Titles are transcribed from original cassette labels, with some additional expansion/information supplied by archivist.
    [Listening copies available in Box 28.]
    - G. Blom 7/3/82-conference; 7/4/82-childhood [Side 1]; G. Blom 7/4/82 childhood; 7/5/82 Italy, Germany [Side 2] (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_001)
    - G. Blom - political yrs 7/4; Europe 7/5, Mexico 1939 [Side A]; 7/5-7/6/82 Early Days Lacandones; 2 Jacinto, Bor [Side B] (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_002)
    - 7/6/82, Missionaries, early Mexico; changes (?), deforestation [Side A]; deforestation, change culture; Na Bolom, Bor & Kin [Side B] (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_003)
    - 7/9/82--Bor and Kin 7/10/82 [Side A]; 7/11/82 Trudi [Blom] on photography, politics--world situation [Side B] (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_004)
    - 7/12, Politics and Frey Bartolomé; 7/13 Education, Franz -- Anthropology (?) [Side A]; 7/14 Trudi [Blom] on Women [Side B] (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_005)
    - 7/14, Woman as photog [photographer]; 7/15 Chan K'in & roman [Side A]; 7/15 Chan K'in & Rivers (?); 7/16 (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_006)
    - G. Blom 7/15/82 (57) 7 on conference [Side A]; G. Blom on Photos 7/20 [Side B] (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_007)
    - Trudi on Photos 7/20 (elec. goes off) [Side A]; Trudi on photos 7/20 [Side B] (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_008)
    - "Blum--Trudi's talk/conference" [Side A]; "Gertrude Blom" [Side B], undated (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_009)
  - A New Life, 1993-1998 and undated
    Biographies of authors and photographers, correspondence, finances and contracts, and printed materials for A New Life: Stories and Photographs from the Suburban South (1997). Arranged alphabetically by topic. Also includes a recording of Harris speaking about his work, circa 1997.
    - A New Life files, (17 folders) (Box 53-54)
    - Inside The Arts: Alex Harris - A New Life, circa 1997 (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_011)
  - A World Unsuspected, 1984-1987 and undated, (3 boxes)
    Manuscripts, recorded lectures, correspondence, copy-edited typescripts, printed materials, and other project files for Harris's book, A World Unsuspected: Portraits of Southern Childhood (1987). Also included here are preparations for a conference at the Lyndhurst Foundation in Chattanooga. Arranged with individual authors's manuscripts first, followed by topical categories in chronological order.
    - A World Unsuspected project files, (54 folders) (Box 55-57)
    - "Alex Harris--A World Unsuspected" [Side A], undated; "Backward Glances Closing" [Side B], 1988 Apr. 23 (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_010)
    - "A World Unsuspected," undated, (4 audiocassettes) (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_014-C_017)
  - South Africa: The Cordoned Heart, circa 1985-1986
    Audiocassettes and micro cassettes of interviews with many of the twenty photographers represented in the Rubenstein Library's South African Documentary Photography Collection, curated by Alex Harris during his work on the project "South Africa: The Cordoned Heart," which resulted in a book published in 1986. Interviews were conducted mainly by Alex Harris and Margaret Sartor. The tapes are mainly undated, but transcripts place them between October 1985 and July 1986. Also includes presentations by Alex Harris and Bruce Payne and others.
    There are fifteen microcassettes and six audiocassettes in this group, arranged in order by last name, then by date. Unidentified tapes are at the end. Includes a set of four cassettes from a Cordoned Heart symposium, 1986. "MC" denotes microcassettes, "C," audiocassettes. Since the transcripts contain little or no reference to the tape numbering scheme, an individual transcript cannot be assumed to contain all appearances of an individual on various tapes. Transcripts are housed in the Correspondence Series under "South Africa--Transcripts."
    [Originals closed to use. Listening copy must be made. Please consult with a reference archivist before coming to use this item.]
    - Alberts, Paul (Sides A, B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_01)
      [Transcript available in Box 42. See also "Unidentified tapes" below.]
    - Alphers, Joseph (Side B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_11)
      [Transcript available in Box 42.]
    - "Badsha at Duke" (Sides A and B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_019)
    - Badsha, Omar
      Badsha's name appears in numerous transcripts; no single transcript is filed under his name. He also appears on these microcassettes: MC_03; MC_04, (A and B); MC_06 (A and B) [plus "Jeewa"]; MC_07 (A and B); MC_10 (Side B); and MC_08 (A and B).
    - Barry, M. [Michael?] (Side A), undated [1985] (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_12)
    - Berman, Bee (Side B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_12)
    - Davies, Michael (Side A), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_03)
    - Gentry, Brenda (Side B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_14)
    - Goldblatt, David--see "Unidentified tapes" below, undated
    - Johnson, Lisa (Side A), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_14)
    - Konings, Paul--see "Unidentified tapes" below, undated
    - Lawson, Lesley (Side B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_09)
    - Ledechowski, Chris (Side B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_03)
    - Ledechowski, Chris (Side A), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_05)
    - Lombard, Rashid (Side B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_05)
    - Lombard, Rashid (Side A), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_12)
    - Lombard, Rashid (Sides A and B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_13)
    - Maclennan, Ben (Side A); Micro2, undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_01)
    - Maclennan, Ben (Side B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_08)
    - Matthews, Jimmy (Side A), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_10)
    - Mendel, Gideon (Side A), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_08)
    - Mendel, Gideon (Side B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_12)
    - Nunn, Cedric (Side A), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_02)
    - Payne, Bruce, and Alex Harris, "Bruce and Alex on S. Africa Duke Talk", undated (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_02)
    - Payne, Bruce, and Alex Harris, speaking on the Cordoned Heart project, undated (Box 27, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_15)
    - Perez, Bernie (Side B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_01)
      [Transcript available?]
    - Peters, Myron, 1985
      [Peters's name is not labeled on a tape, but a transcript is available in Box 42.]
    - South Africa: The Cordoned Heart Symposium, ICP [four audiocassettes labeled Side 1 -- Side 7], 1986 May 9 (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_020-C_023)
    - Sparks, Allister (sides A and B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_C_024)
    - Weinberg, Paul (A); see also "Unidentified tapes" below. (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_11)
    - W. [Weinberg], Paul (A and B); see also "Unidentified tapes" below. (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_04)
    - Unidentified: GBlatt [Goldblatt?] (Side B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_02)
    - Unidentified: Paul [could mean Alberts, Konings, or Weinberg] (Side B), undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_05)
    - Unidentified: Side A may also refer to Goldblatt, undated (Box 62, Audiocassette RL_10060_MC_09)
  - Other Projects
    - Notebook with "Bill Hawley" on cover (Director of Educational Programs in Public Policy at Duke Univ.) with notes on education programs in NC, and other loose notes on same, 1978 and undated
    - Script from a talk concerning Harris's documentary film work (in partnership with Paula Erlich), The Time of Our lives: Living With Brain Cancer, circa 2012
- Teaching Materials Series, 1976-2004, (3 boxes)
  Syllabi, printed materials, student writings, and other classroom materials for Harris's classes at University of North Carolina and Duke University. Arranged chronologically.
  [SOME MATERIALS MAY BE RESTRICTED: Students's grades and social security numbers have been redacted in all places where they were encountered. Any similar information remaining in the files is closed to use and must be removed.]
  - Classes at UNC and Duke, 1976-1996, (32 folders) (Box 58-60)
  - Student Photographic Work, DOC, 2003-2004, (13 items) (Box 61)
    Color photographs documenting North Carolina State Fairgrounds and Durham, North Carolina urban scenes, produced by three students taking Alex Harris's course, PPS/DOCST 177S, academic year 2003-2004. Consists of nine inkjet 9x13 inch color prints and four paper-format text panels, including the introductory text panel by Harris. Some of the students's work was exhibited in 2004 at the Center for Documentary Studies under the title Sense of Place. List of titles available in the box.
- Oversize Materials
  - Kwilecki, Paul: proofs and other documents from Kwilecki's photography book, Understandings (removed from Correspondence Series) (Box 61)
  - Printed materials and publicity, various projects, 1975-1991 and undated, (5 folders)
  - Lyon, Danny, Memories of the Southern Civil Rights Movement, proofs, 1992, (4 folders)